Hey, Shaan this side. Welcome to Concept
and Coding. And in the previous video,
we have already seen the JPA
architecture and its life cycle and how
to set up.
In this video, I'll tell you a very
important first level caching.
But if you have not seen the previous
video, I would highly recommend it
because it's totally dependent on it.
In case, if you missed it, I will just
briefly explain the life cycle. I will
not again tell it in depth, just one use
case
because without this, first level
caching would be like incomplete if you
have not watched the previous video and
directly jumping here. So, just to
maintain a context, uh let me take 2
minutes to quickly uh revise the life
cycle of it.
So, here, just with the very simple one
example, I will show you this. Let's say
that I am creating user entity
a equals to new user
entity.
This is my one uh user entity created.
I am creating a transaction,
okay? And I'm doing begin.
I am doing
entity manager
.
persist
a, this object.
Then I am saying that, "Okay,
I want to remove it. Entity
manager.remove
a."
Then again, I change my mind. Hey,
entity manager
. persist.
Okay?
And then I say that,
"Commit."
Finish. So, what would happen as per the
life cycle of this?
So, whenever you are creating a new
entity,
it is currently in the new state.
Okay?
So, when you created a transaction and
calls the entity manager.persist
means you want to insert into DB.
You are not directly dealing with the
DB.
So, entity manager is provided API and
its API is provided by hibernate
session.impl. In that, first it will
goes to
persistence context. So, this is your
persistence context.
It will manage this entity.
So, currently
A is over here.
Okay, it's not there into the DB even
though you have called persist,
remember.
Now, let's say that you have called
remove. Hey, I want to remove it, delete
it.
So, it will goes to a new state called
remove.
So, again, it is inside a persistence
context
but estate of the entity has been
changed. Now, A is present here.
Its estate has been changed to remove.
But, again, it's not there into the DB.
Remove means
whenever the data is flushed
it will get removed from the DB.
From your perceptive, you have first
inserted and then you are removing it.
But, actual DB is not yet comes into the
picture because everything is currently
happening in the persistence context.
Now, you said that no, no, I want it
again
and I want to persist it. So, it will
again goes back to the persistent
estate. Now, A is here. So, you know
that
your entity estate
entity estate or you can say that life
cycle is
current from new to manage to remove or
you can even detach it. Okay, you can do
whatever. But, once you do commit, means
you are flushing it to the DB. You are
syncing it with the DB. If it is managed
then you are flushing it, it goes there
and insert it.
If it is already there, A is already
there, and it is in removed state, now
you do flush,
it will remove it. Then it is actually
removed from the DB.
So, till commit means commit is the time
when actual flush happen. So, till flush
happens, everything is handled in
memory.
That's handled through persistence
context. And that's what helps in the
first level caching. So, now let's see
one example. So, very very basic example
which in the previous video we have
created. So, I have created one test JPA
interface
API.
There I have created a user.
Okay? Now, I am trying to save it into
DB. I am calling the user service API.
And after inserting, I am doing a select
query. So, this is my expectation.
First, I am inserting, and and then I am
fetching.
So, during insert, I am calling user
detail service save.
And internally, it is dealing with user
repository. User detail repository is
just an interface which I have written
which extend JPA repository. That's all.
So, this is very very basic which we
have already seen. Now, if I start an
application,
now I am starting an application, you
will see that
the first it drops and create a table
because we are using in-memory DB.
Okay?
Now, I am creating hitting this API,
test JPA.
So, what is the expectation before I
hit? Expectation is
first it will insert,
then it will make one select query.
Let's hit it.
So, here if you say that we are able to
see the data.
Now, we are able to see one insert. Yes,
but where is the select query?
Why there is no select query is there?
But how come I am able to fetch the
data.
It's because of cache.
Okay, so what is happening inside? How
the first level caching works? So, let's
see what is happening.
So, when this API is invoked, when this
API is invoked,
what it is doing is
what it is doing is it is first calling
save user.
Okay? So, when the save user is
happening,
so it is calling
this JPA repository save user.
Okay, so internally you know that,
right? What would happen? So, inside a
save user,
internally it's using an entity manager
calling persist. Okay? Internally it is
calling
entity manager
\dot} persist.
Now, if you remember, I told you that
whenever entity manager persist was
there, so this is nothing but a method
interface.
Session IMPL
is the one Hibernate provided an
implementation for this persist.
And when the persist is happen, we are
creating a
persistence context.
Okay? And this persistence context,
whatever the object entity you want to
create, it first hold it.
Okay? So, you never interact directly
with DB. If you understand this
lifecycle, you will get to know that
DB only comes into the picture when we
do commit, when we do flush.
Till then, everything is there, the
state of the entity is
there by the persistence context only.
So, we can say that one entity manager
equals to one persistence context.
If you have two entity manager, it will
have another persistence context. So,
one-to-one mapping.
And this second persistence context
is totally isolated from one another.
There is no interaction.
If any data is present here,
this data is not visible to us.
Okay?
So, now in this what happening is when
you are doing
doing save user, internally it is
calling entity manager.persist. So,
means it is able to find an entity
manager first. It is able to find an
entity manager object. So, means entity
manager is there.
And it when it is doing persist,
internally it first create a persistence
context.
And it stores the data.
This entity
user detail this is stored there.
Okay, so let's see that. So, here it
calls save user.
So, internally it calls this and the
control comes to
this save.
Right? This is what simple JPA
repository, right? We are calling JPA
repository itself.
User service and user service is calling
JPA repository. So, it will comes here.
Now, here it is calling entity
manager.persist.
So, you know that it will go into the
session.impl and from that session it
will create a persistence context. So,
now here if you see,
it is adding the entity.
So, it will put in in the map.
It will put if it is absent. What? This
key.
What is the key? This user which you're
trying to insert.
This one.
This user which you're trying to save.
So, it will create a key and it insert
into the map. And the object is your
complete object.
Okay, now data is present here.
Now data is
present here. From earlier you created a
new object, you call persist. Now data
is present here.
Save is
annotated with at the rate
transactional. Means, if you remember
from the transactional video,
there is a transactional interceptor
which do begin and commit. So, means
commit has happened. So, at this time
flush would have happened. So, it would
have inserted make one insert query.
Also.
So, data is there into this uh
persistence and it has flushed into the
DB also. Now DB is in sync.
Now you are doing get query. So, one
insert query is done. One insert query
is done.
Now you are doing get user. Again, when
you are doing a get user,
okay, by primary key, what happens?
Let's see that.
When we are doing get user or let's say
that find by ID. One one ID I'm trying
to fetch, right? So, internally what it
does?
Again, entity manager.
So, currently
it is trying able to find the same
entity manager object.
Okay, so this is also working with the
same entity manager which is this is
working.
When this the same entity manager is you
are working with, means the same
persistence context it is aware of and
if that persistence context has that
data,
it will not even go to DB.
So, when the get user happen, so what
would happen is
when you call find by ID, get user,
internally it call find by ID and find
by ID, you know that session
IMPL and session IMPL internally
calls persistence context and their get
entity.
So, whatever the key map we have
created, it try to fetch the key.
Now here, since it is the same
entity manager,
we are using the same entity manager,
same persistence context is used, and
that's why it is able to fetch the data.
So, no select query,
no select query is hit. It returned from
the cache.
Now you can ask me a question that
Hey Sean,
how the same entity manager is used?
I'll show you. In the dispatch If you go
little deep in the you will al- already
get to know
if you go inside dispatcher servlet, you
know that dispatcher servlet is the
first controller.
So, in the dispatcher servlet, there is
something called apply pre-handle.
Before it actually invokes the
controller, there is a pre-handle.
And this pre-handle here, if you see,
whatever the during application is start
up, in the previous video we have seen,
right? It creates an entity manager
factory. It fetches that factory and
creates the entity manager.
So, for each
HTTP request,
one entity manager is created by
default.
Remember that, right?
So, I have created
one HTTP request. Now if you see,
now when I call the first like test JPA.
When I call this API, one HTTP request
means one entity manager
and one persistence context.
Okay? Now whenever I do DB query, save,
get,
right? So, the same entity manager is
used, means same persistence context.
So, whatever the data is is present into
the persistence context, it will return
me.
Okay? Now here, if you see, I have
created one more API, read JPA.
It is doing direct get user, this same
only. It is trying to fetch.
If I call new API \slash} read \hyphen}
JPA,
new API means new HTTP request I'm
hitting. I'm hitting new API, right? New
HTTP request.
New HTTP request means second entity
means new entity manager it will create.
And new entity manager means new
persistence context.
And it do not know about the data which
is present into another persistence
context.
So, it will make a select query, fresh
select query here.
It will make a fresh select query here.
Let's see this one, okay?
So, in the entity controller,
I have two APIs, one test JPA.
This has save user
and find by ID.
And then I have read JPA. There I have
two select query, two times.
Just two time find.
Okay?
And
also, let me put a debugger point in
stateful persistence manager at entity
state.
So, I am starting a debugger point.
So, when I started the application, you
know that fresh table is started because
we are using H2 database in memory.
Now, I'm first calling test JPA. I am
hitting it.
So, see, I am trying to do first save.
Because test JPA, what is the
functionality? We are first inserting
and then query.
So, first inserting. It goes inside
save.
Okay? So, entity manager.
So, it goes to entity manager.process.
So, now see, if you are doing process,
what would happen is
it will first try to insert this entity
into the
persistence context map, cache, you can
say that. So, this is my entity, this is
the key.
So, it is inserting into this.
After that,
it has committed it because he save is
transaction, so committed happen.
Okay, so means insert query might have
happened.
Now, it is trying to do controller is
trying to do
the get query. So, now it is doing find
by ID.
So, here if you see, will it go to DB?
First, it will check the persistence
context that, "Hey, is data is present
into the entities by key?" See, this is
a map.
The key is there.
And what is the key it's trying to look?
Yes, the same.
So, it has the data
and it will return it.
Now, if you see the console,
insert query happened, but there is no
select query.
Because same persistence manager is used
because it is created at the one HTTP
request.
Now, see, application is still running.
Data might be present into the DB yet.
Like uh if we connect the DB,
application is running, data is there.
Now, if I am running another read
\hyphen}jpa. So, in read\hyphen}jpa,
what is happening?
Two times.
Two times
find by ID is happening.
Now,
I told you whenever a new request, so
I'm going to hit this, so new HTTP
request, new entity manager.
New entity manager doesn't know about
the previous entity manager persistence
context. It will create its own.
So, for the first time, it will has to
go to the DB, fetch this data from the
DB.
But and then it will put into its
persistence context.
And the second time
the select query it would be a cache
hit. So only one time select query we
should be able to see.
So let's hit it.
So I am calling find by ID.
Okay. So first I am hitting get entity.
Will it be able to get the entity? Here
if you see, null.
No. It will goes to the DB.
Found find the data, insert it. It will
adding it. Now second time it is
hitting.
Will it be able to find it? Yes, it able
to find.
Holder is there.
Second time there is no hit. Now if you
see the console,
only one select query.
Sometimes
we get difficulty in understanding this.
I have shown you by running this itself.
So we can also run this
by using our own creating own entity
manager. So you can also try using this.
So in the service class
I am creating a entity manager factory,
auto wired it.
Object is created at the time of
application itself. I am just auto
wiring it. Same object would be used.
So now I am creating first session. In
Hibernate terms I will say that session
is created.
Means I am creating entity manager
object through factory.
After that I started the transaction.
I am doing persist and two times fetch.
So means three DB queries.
Okay.
And then I am printing it and then I am
committing the transaction here. I am
doing flushing here and then closing the
entity.
So this session is closed here.
So now if you see that what happening is
when you are running this code
first session is created means entity
manager knows about the DB like from
this entity manager
factory
it knows how to interact with the DB.
So, it will entity manager would be
created.
Purchase user. So, this user would be
inserted first. So, what if it is a
fresh user? So, first insert
So, first persistence context would be
created.
Insert this user, let's say hashtag one.
Key would be
created and the value
So, one and then it make an insert
query.
Okay?
Insert query would be
made during this commit flush.
Okay?
Now, after that a find come.
So, it is using the same entity manager,
right? Now, it is easy to visualize.
Same entity manager it's using. So, when
it do find means
same persistence context, currently data
is not there into the DB because I we
have not done the flush.
Okay? So, it's there only in the
persistence context.
Now, I'm doing find. So, find
will it be able to find? Yes.
So, no DB query is required. Again, I am
doing
will it require again DB query? No.
Same entity manager, same persistence
context, able to find it.
So, no. After that, I am printing it and
doing committing.
Now, during this commit it do the flush.
So, means now insert query will go.
And this user is also go
entry goes here into the DB.
Now, the second time I am doing
another entity manager. Second entity
manager is created.
Second entity manager means new
persistence context.
I am creating a transaction, committing
it here.
So, now I am first trying to find.
Find the one.
Does this entity manager knows about
this persistence context? Let's say that
even though I am not closing this entity
manager.
It's open, let's say.
But
will this know about this persistence
context? No, this is separate entity
manager.
It knows about its persistent context
only.
So, it will try to hit a query.
Okay, it don't know about it. So, when
it do find
it find it no, then it goes to the DB.
DB already has that data user one.
So, it will bring it and add it here.
Okay.
So, one time select query happen at this
time.
After that it will do again find. Second
time find comes. Now it will goes to
persistence context.
Now it find yes. Now it does it need to
go to the DB? No, it is already found
the data. So, it return it.
Data is found, then I do commit. So,
there is nothing to flush. It's only get
query.
And then it will close it.
So, one insert, one select query happen.
So, now here if you see application is
start up.
So, one insert
at this time.
And one
select query
at this time.
So, I hope you able to clarify how it is
working.
Okay.
And I already told you very important,
it's very easy to remember entity
manager is created at an HTTP request.
Because even though we are calling uh
repository, JPA repository, like save
query
internally it only goes ahead and find
out the entity manager. We always find
confusion. Hey, does it pick one entity
manager, different entity manager? Will
it be able to cache it or not?
I always easy to remember that
dispatcher servlet is the one which
create a entity manager at the time of
every HTTP request.
So, this is known as first
level caching.
Okay, where
two entity manager, one entity manager
have their own persistence context
and they both are independent to each
other and isolated.
Okay, any call from
individual
entity manager
persistence context help in doing the
managing the caching from this. There is
no knowledge of inter
persistence context.
That's where second
level caching comes into the picture. We
will see it later.
Okay, guys. Thank you. If you have any
question, we can discuss in the comment
section. Thank you. Bye.